what is a great disappointment well um
the millerite movement
believed that something was going to
happen in 1844
they believed that jesus was going to
return to the earth
to cleanse the sanctuary jesus did not
return to the earth in 1844
it was called the great disappointment
remember that we talked about this
the 70-week prophecy
began with the restoration of the
sanctuary
god's people being led out of out of
captivity the restoration of the
sanctuary
what happened in the 70-week prophecy on
a literal local level
happens on a larger level with a 2300
day prophecy
and let me explain what i mean by this
in
1331 a.d
the disciples were under the impression
that jesus was about to set up his
kingdom
on earth remember they walked with jesus
three and a half years
they talked with him he taught them and
yet
they did not rightly understand his
mission so what happens when jesus dies
the disciples experience a
great disappointment
oh that's interesting the disappointment
was
they did not understand the events of
the 70 week prophecy
the first part of the 2 300 days
right so what happens
three days later you have jesus
resurrecting from the grave he is on the
road
remember the the the disciples on the
road to emmaus
and and jesus reveals to the disciples
on the road to the
emmaus they're probably walking through
a you know i don't know a cornfield or
something i don't know
they're probably walking somewhere
really really discouraged right
and and they're probably like maybe
wanting to hide their faces from people
because it's like
man we were just we were preaching that
jesus was about to come
and do this and that and we were wrong
yeah and it's on the road to amaze that
these two disciples
get the glimpse of what actually
was to transpire their great
disappointment
turned into the cornerstone of the
movement
all right just check that out the thing
that you would think they would be most
embarrassed of
man we were preaching that jesus was
gonna come and set up camp on earth
that thing became the cornerstone
that's what caused the movement to grow
so rapidly
so watch this jesus resurrects
right and then he ascends to heaven so
what are the disciples going around and
saying now
oh jesus isn't a heavenly sanctuary
and what are the jews saying to in
response to this
man y'all are y'all are making up face
savings
oh okay so first people come in
i'm good first he was coming to do this
and y'all got that wrong so oh now
he's in a heavenly sanctuary
where we can't see him huh yeah i guess
where he's standing in the midst of
seven candlesticks and so watch this
guys
the very same events that occurred
at the at the 70 week prophecy
whoa very interesting
that that ver the very same
circumstances
occur in 1844 amen
because it is after this great
disappointment that you have two
of the that would be the pioneers of our
movement walking in a cornfield they're
discouraged they're depressed they're
like man we don't want anyone to see our
faith
we have messed up we don't even know how
we messed up
they're not denying that they messed up
but they're embarrassed
when it suddenly is revealed to them
by the spirit of god that the sanctuary
to be cleansed
was not an earthly temple was not this
earth which is what they were under the
impression of
the earth is the temple christ is coming
to cleanse the temple
no no no no there's a heavenly sanctuary
and that's what we began to look at the
the the old testament type of the
sanctuary to see that the day of
atonement was about the high priest
moving from one phase of ministry
to final phase of ministry yeah
so the very thing that was to be our
embarrassment
oh yeah let's not talk about 1844. have
you become the very
cornerstone of our take that away from
us
take away the great disappointment from
us and we have no reason to exist as a
movement
making up stuff because you got it wrong
so oh
yeah now christ moved from one
compartment
or one phase of ministry to another
phase of ministry
y'all are just making stuff up to save
face
very great good i mean i that was yeah
it opened my mind